<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jayanth Prathipati</title>
    <description>UX Researcher | Software Developer | Designer</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 19:14:20 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 19:14:20 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>MeterMaid</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-project&quot;&gt;About This Project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt; Summary &lt;/h3&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Domain &lt;/b&gt;| Crowdsourcing &lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills &lt;/b&gt;| Literature Review, Prototyping, Competitive Analysis, Screen Mockups, Reframing, Persona &amp;amp; Scenario Generation  &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tools&lt;/b&gt; | Sketch, Principle, and Invision&lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role&lt;/b&gt; | Researcher &amp;amp; Designer&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team&lt;/b&gt; | Jayanth Prathipati, &lt;a href=&quot;http://carolinewin.com&quot;&gt;Shannon Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;, Rho Eun Song, and Kathy Liu &lt;/p&gt; 
          &lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
          &lt;h3&gt;Problem Space&lt;/h3&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Parking is expensive and difficult to find, yet some research suggests that around 3 parking spaces exist for every car. How can a resource seem scarce, yet actually be so abundant? One contributing factor is that some spaces can only be utilized by a specific person, like a driveway at someone’s house. When the homeowner is away, their driveway is unoccupied, making it an unutilized resource. Is it possible to make these exclusive resources available to others when their primary owner is not using them? And why doesn’t this happen now? One contributing factor is that there is a mutual lack of trust between the person with the driveway and the person looking for parking.
 &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MeterMaid is an application that enables homeowners to capitalize upon their open driveway space by connecting with drivers seeking convenient and affordable parking. We designed it specifically to facilitate trust between the two parties, particularly on the homeowner’s side by enabling them to monitor their property in the application, report inappropriate or malicious behavior, and filter out and block certain users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 15:33:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/metermaid</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/metermaid</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ScottyChat</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-project&quot;&gt;About This Project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt; Summary &lt;/h3&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Domain &lt;/b&gt;| Education/Social &lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills &lt;/b&gt;| Journey Mapping, Prototyping, Competitive Analysis, Screen Mockups, Reframing, Persona &amp;amp; Scenario Generation  &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tools&lt;/b&gt; | Sketch, Invision&lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role&lt;/b&gt; | Researcher &amp;amp; Designer&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team&lt;/b&gt; | Jayanth Prathipati and &lt;a href=&quot;http://carolinewin.com&quot;&gt;Caroline Win&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; 
          &lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
          &lt;h3&gt;Problem Space&lt;/h3&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;While there is a lot of information available for undergraduate programs in the USA. Finding information about Graduate Programs can be quite difficult. There aren't many resources available online. In addition, finding accounts of student life and job opportunities from the program can be scarce as well. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created ScottyChat, a crowd sourced chatbot that lets you interact with Scotty the Dog, the CMU Mascot. Scotty helps admitted students connect with an alumni mentor in your location and profession. Scotty gives students $10 to buy their mentor a coffee. In addition, Scotty will answer general questions about CMU and the MHCI program through the use of Machine Learning. It will funnel more complex or challenging questions to the current MHCI cohort. This saves time for the current cohort so that they don’t answer the same questions over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;initial-research&quot;&gt;Initial Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we interviewed 4 Masters students about their experiences from getting accepted into the program to arriving at Carnegie Mellon and created journey maps to get a better understanding of how the experience was for them. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_1.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
	   	&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	   		&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_3.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consolidated our journey map to get a better understanding of the typical master student’s journey at CMU&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_journey_initial.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-insights-from-journey-mapping&quot;&gt;Key Insights from Journey Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From journey mapping, we gained the following insights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students felt most distressed and overwhelmed while deciding whether to attend CMU because of the associated time and financial costs, the multitude of differing opinions about the program, and the lack of information about the value gained through the program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition, students felt a steep dropoff after signing the acceptance letter, because there were so many tasks to complete, too many sources of information, and little direction on forms to fill out and how to register for classes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preparing to move was also a stressful experience due to the need to find appropriate roommates and housing, pack up and move stuff, and tie up loose ends at work or at home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that most students asked these general questions such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I register for classes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the cost of tuition?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When is the due date to apply for loans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is Pittsburgh cold?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also asked Career-Oriented Questions such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are job opportunities like for students who graduate from the program?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What will I gain from doing this program?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prototyping&quot;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We envisioned some solutions to solve the problems and help answer the questions that students set out. We wanted to reduce the troughs in the previous journey map and make that experience a lot better for incoming students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a round of visioning and came up with 15 possible solutions to solve some of these problems. We quickly realized that we were interested in helping give advice to incoming students and give them a personal mentorship experience. Every student we interviewed mentioned that they talked to alumni and that was huge reason for why they pursued the masters program at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created the following scenarios and created paper and pencil prototypes to evaluate our idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scenario-1&quot;&gt;Scenario #1:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark just got accepted into the MHCI program at CMU and some other great colleges. He wants to make the best decision for his future and is debating between all of his choices.
When he is stressing out, he receives an email from Scotty to see if he needs help making his decision. He logs onto “ScottyChat” and sees that he can ask questions to Scotty the dog or get connected with an alumni. Scotty helps Mark get connected with an alumni through a few quick questions about his location and future interests (PM, Designer, Dev). Scotty helps him match up with alumni mentor John, and they are able to grab coffee at CMU and talk about what MHCI has to offer. Mark is very happy coming out of his meeting and signs his acceptance letter at CMU!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scenario-2&quot;&gt;Scenario #2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s April. Jenny graduated last Fall from the MHCI program at CMU and is currently working as an UX Designer at IBM in San Francisco. She had a great time at CMU and wants to stay connected to the community. When checking her e-mail on Monday morning, she sees a message from Scotty. “Hey Tartan! We miss you! Ben is a prospective MHCI student in San Francisco and wants to learn more about the program. Will you help him out? Get some free coffee while you’re at it!” Well, I’m free this Saturday. I think I could take an hour to get coffee with Ben, she thinks. She clicks on the message and opens ScottyChat. Ben and Jenny have a quick conversation and plan to meet on Saturday at 2pm. After they meet, Ben feels much more informed about the program and is excited to attend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scenario-3&quot;&gt;Scenario #3&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark is getting ready to move into Pittsburgh and prepare for CMU. He is an avid gym-goer and is confused about what the gym is like at CMU. He wants to figure out if it’s got all of the right equipment and see if there’s a good gym in the neighborhood. He logs into ScottyChat and asks Scotty: “What is the gym like at the UC? I lift freeweights, and I was wondering if the CMU gym has equipment for that? Should I be looking for gyms in Shadyside?” Mark’s question gets routed to the MHCI slack channel where various people are able to look at the question and respond quickly. Mark gets a response from Scotty stating: “Here’s what other people have said: “The UC gym has a ton of equipment but it gets crowded, it might be worth it to get a membership at X Shadyside. It costs $55 per month (pricey) but it’s never crowded”
Mark is able to use this information and figure out what subscription he needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of our paper prototypes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
	   	&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	   		&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-4&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had users walk through our prototypes using those scenarios and got some great insights. Primarily we found out that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People loved the idea of talking to Scotty the Dog. anthropomorphizing our chatbot worked really well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users found it confusing that the Chatbot was crowd sourced as well as automated. We needed to make that idea more clear to the users.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition, they found it hard to understand who to ask questions to. They didn’t know whether to ask questions to Scotty or to their mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, we created round of prototypes and focused on making the Scotty and mentorships separate entities and making it easier for the user to understand what each entity is there for (Scotty is for general questions, and mentors are for deeper career-oriented and personal questions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_7.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 
	   	&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
	   		&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_8.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_9.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then demoed these screens and feedback on our visual design. We found that users found part of our flow to be a little bit confusing and wanted to make sure that we had a uniform design from mobile to desktop. We had used slightly different icons in place that made it a little bit harder to use at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our changes, we made Invision prototypes for both the mobile and deskop flows. I’ve linked them below for you to play with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;438&quot; height=&quot;930&quot; src=&quot;//invis.io/TK8VTWQN8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;evaluate&quot;&gt;Evaluate&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After creating these prototypes, we did a final round of evaluation and tried to better view where our end users would be. We did a journey map of a user with our invisioned solution and found that they would be a better experience overall. We were able to add benefits to the university and to the end user and make their admittance experience better overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12&quot;&gt;
	    	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scotty_10.png&quot; /&gt;
	    &lt;/div&gt; 

&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 15:33:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/scottychat</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/scottychat</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MindMapper: a investigation into bringing insight to EEG Devices</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-project&quot;&gt;About This Project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt; Summary &lt;/h3&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Domain &lt;/b&gt;| Mobile Health/Quantified Self &lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills &lt;/b&gt;| prototyping, illustration, heuristic evaluation, persona generation, contextual inquiry, affinity diagramming, and android development  &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tools&lt;/b&gt; | Sketch, Android Studio&lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role&lt;/b&gt; | Researcher, Designer, Developer&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team&lt;/b&gt; | Jayanth Prathipati and &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.cs.vt.edu/rbeaton/&quot;&gt;Bobby Beaton&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor)  &lt;/p&gt; 
          &lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
          &lt;h3&gt;Problem Space&lt;/h3&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;With the advent of wearables and smart phones, tracking your physical activity has been getting easier. However, tracking your mental focus has not changed. we wanted to explore how we could use EEG devices (think Fitbits but for mental activity instead of physical) and see if we could bring the power of these devices to market. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built an Android app that interfaced with EEG devices to help give actionable feedback to users. Our primary challenge was educating the market on EEG devices and helping users to gain a deeper understanding of how their mental focus trends throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    We performed a literature review on quantified-self technologies as well as doing some competitive analysis on what is currently on the market, reading relevant research papers such as such as: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://research.microsoft.com/apps/pubs/default.aspx?id=163348&quot;&gt;AffectAura&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.academia.edu/2518447/NeuroPlace_Making_sense_of_a_place&quot;&gt;NeuroPlace&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://infovis.cs.vt.edu/oldsite/papers/CHI02-periphvis.pdf&quot;&gt;An Ordering of Secondary Task Display Attributes&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;br /&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;
    In addition, we intereviewed users with attentional difficulties and tried to get a better understanding of their daily routines. I used this data to create some personas of our target users. 
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;
    We gained some key insights from this research: 
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Users define focus based on the context that they are in. It could mean something different per user and also per activity.  
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Users are focused around increasing productivity
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Users are able to interpret this data well when it is used in conjunction with context such as location and activity
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/competitive_analysis.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;post-caption&quot;&gt;Existing Visualizations in Self-Tracking Apps&lt;/p&gt;






&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created a series of personas and use cases from our initial research. We were specifically interested in how a user would use this product daily and we centered our use cases and personas based on that specific interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prototyping&quot;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created multiple prototypes in order to evaluate MindMapper. 
I created paper and pencil prototypes and made them interactive using Marvel. I then ran a quick heuristic review with my teammates to better understand if the information visualizations that I created made sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/mindmapper_lo_fi.png&quot; style=&quot;width:35em; height:45em;  display: block;     margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;post-caption&quot;&gt;Lo-Fi prototype of MindMapper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We quickly learned that some visualizations were very hard to use. Users used color as an indicator for strength rather than size. We quickly focused on another round of lo-fi prototyping and review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we created a hi-fi sketch prototype that gave target users a better idea of langugage, icons, and notifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://marvelapp.com/68d492?emb=1&quot; width=&quot;390&quot; height=&quot;755&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;evaluation&quot;&gt;Evaluation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on our previous results, we quickly found out that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users didn’t understand the meaning of mental focus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design metaphors such as the focus score and the attention score didn’t make sense to users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users felt like the flow of the app didn’t make much sense&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on these results, I led the development team to make quick 
changes to the app to better fit the mental models for users and create a faster user flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work won 6 awards at the Virginia Tech Undergraduate Research Symposium and got over $2000 of research funding money. We’re proud of this work and hope to release an open source Android app to let people use their EEG’s with their devices in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 15:33:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/mindmapper</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/mindmapper</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jhana: An exploration of the Experience Sampling Method</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-project&quot;&gt;About This Project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt; Summary &lt;/h3&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Domain &lt;/b&gt;| Mobile Health/Quantified Self &lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills &lt;/b&gt;| prototyping, usability testing, contextual inquiry, interviewing, illustration, iOS+watchOS development (Obj-C) &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tools&lt;/b&gt; | Sketch, Xcode&lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role&lt;/b&gt; | Lead Researcher, Designer, and Back End Developer&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team&lt;/b&gt; | Jayanth Prathipati, &lt;a href=&quot;http://schung7.github.io&quot;&gt;Steven Chung&lt;/a&gt; (Lead Front End Developer &amp;amp; designer), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.cs.vt.edu/rbeaton/&quot;&gt;Bobby Beaton&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor)  &lt;/p&gt; 
          &lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
          &lt;h3&gt;Problem Space&lt;/h3&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;With the advent of wearables and smart phones, tracking your physical activity has been getting easier. However, tracking your mental focus has not changed. we wanted to explore how we could use the devices that are in our pockets and on our wrists to help us better track what we are doing and see how that could change our behaviors over time.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built an Apple Watch and iPhone app called Jhana that allowed users to self-report their attention. Users get notifications to fill out small 5 second surveys throughout the day on their watch and their phone and get to view graphs and additional insights on their surveys in the corresponding iPhone app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    We performed a literature review on quantified-self technologies as well as doing some competitive analysis on what is currently on the market. 
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    We also interviewed students who tracking them own activity in various ways such as using Fitbits, Apple Watch, or even manual diary entries like MyFitnessPal and used this data to construct an affinity diagram as well a hierarchical task analysis.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    We gained some key insights from this research: 
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Primarily, we found out that user's felt that entering in activity in apps like MyFitnessPal had a lot of mental strain and felt stressed out when filling out this information. 
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      In addition, we found that once users settled into a routine, they didn't find these devices as important anymore as they already knew what insights the Fitbit or MyFitnessPal app would tell them.
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/affinity_jh.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;post-caption&quot;&gt;Affinity Diagram from our interviews&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prototyping&quot;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built low-fi paper prototypes and built a marvel prototype to test our interface. We quickly found that our data entry process was fairly straight forward and didn’t get many complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then moved to a higher fidelity prototype so that we could test some of our interactions on iPhone and Apple Watch. We wanted to make extensive use of swiping on both of these devices since it is a natural and intuitive gesture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to intuitive gestures, We wanted to make use of the hardware features of the Apple Watch, such as the digital crown (knob on the side of the Apple Watch) and make the app feel at home on a user’s home screen rather than a research project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring these ideas to fruition, I designed a swiping leikert scale to make it easier and delightful for users to select how focused they were. Here are examples of this interaction on iPhone and Apple Watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//giphy.com/embed/wBHZfKccOgA5q&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;859&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//giphy.com/embed/26FL9ovWI3vCtLU1a&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;683&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built out our iPhone app using the interactions we learned from these interactions. We used Core Data to create a local database and made use of a lot of App Kit features such as storyboards and auto-layout to make our app compatible with all screen sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;evaluation&quot;&gt;Evaluation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran a 2 day user study to study how using a wearable device would change user’s attention. We did pre and post study interviews to understand our users and get their opinions on the product. In addition to that, I integrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.yahoo.com/analytics/&quot;&gt;Flurry Analytics&lt;/a&gt;  into our iPhone and WatchOS app in order to log usage information of the app such as how long users took in order to fill out a survey. We initially thought that users would favor having the combination of an Apple Watch and iPhone and would be able to perform tasks faster. However, we came to some interesting conclusions from our findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We found out that users “felt” that the watch app was much easier to log entries with….however, from our Flurry dashboard we found that the time difference between the watch and the iPhone apps was very small&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We found that users were in fact changing their behavior based after using our app. One user reported to us that she changed her studying habits after getting notifications from the app.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also found that users were not yet acquainted with Apple Watch. Most of our drawbacks came from lack of Apple Watch education. If we performed the study again, we would spend additional time prompting users on how to use the Apple Watch and teach them additional functionality on how to use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 15:33:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/jhana</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/jhana</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jobs: A look into Data Viz and Machine Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.7.2/leaflet.js?2&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.7.3/leaflet.css&quot; /&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/js/dragdealer.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;link href=&quot;/css/dragdealer.css&quot; type=&quot;text/css&quot; rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; /&gt;

&lt;link href=&quot;/css/graph.css&quot; type=&quot;text/css&quot; rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-project&quot;&gt;About This Project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px; margin-right:0px;&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt; Summary &lt;/h3&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Domain &lt;/b&gt;| Machine Learning/Data Visualization &lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills &lt;/b&gt;| Machine Learning, Python development, Front End Web Development &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tools&lt;/b&gt; | Python (SciPy, NumPy, Pandas, and Beautiful Soup), D3.js, Leaflet.js&lt;/p&gt; 
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role&lt;/b&gt; | Lead Web Developer and Data Scientist&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team&lt;/b&gt; | Jayanth Prathipati and &lt;a href=&quot;http://oliverek.com&quot;&gt;Oliver Ebeling-Koning&lt;/a&gt; (Lead Data Scientist) &lt;/p&gt; 
          &lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&gt;
          &lt;h3&gt;Problem Space&lt;/h3&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Software professionals are in demand in a lot of places in the world. In addition, they have an opportunity that few others have had before; the ability to work remote. We were curious about what trends were formed in a software developer's job search (being a software developer myself...it seemed like a good thing to look into). In addition, as software developers, we were curious about pay distribution for specific features such as location and programming language of choice. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/&quot;&gt;Beautiful Soup&lt;/a&gt; to parse &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/jobs&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow jobs&lt;/a&gt;, a website with job listings for software developers. We used data about these job listings, such as location, salary, and programming language of choice to see if there would be any clustering. In addition, we were curious about what programming language had the highest starting salaries. Finally, we were curious about how location influenced salary size, we looked into average cost of living and tried to see where developers would get the most in-pocket income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-cleaning&quot;&gt;Data Cleaning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We initially had to clean all of the data and try to get the closest major city to a lot of minor locations. For example, we could get a job listing for Queens, New York. We needed to have a way to figure out if that was in the New York metropolitan area. We used reverse geocoding to get the general area of a job and sort our listings by metro locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-results&quot;&gt;Final Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cleaning our data, we fed this data into NumPy to perform K-Means clustering in order to make better sense of the data. We found (to no surprise)
that jobs were centered around various tech hubs around the US such as S.F, NYC, and Austin. We did find some surprises, namely that Chicago and Atlanta had lots of tech jobs. Chicago had approximately 208 job listings and Atlanta had approximately 63. We have listed two visualizations that we built to better show our results. Please check them below. They are unfortunately not responsive, so please look at them on a laptop or desktop device!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
Here is a choropleth map that cumulates all of the developer jobs in the USA. Slide the bar below to see a count of developer jobs for a specific language!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;map&quot; style=&quot;height: 440px; border: 1px solid #AAA;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;just-a-slider&quot; class=&quot;dragdealer&quot; style=&quot;width: 800px&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;handle red-bar&quot; style=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Map that shows the different clusters that were generated based on the Jobs data. We overlaid a subsample of the raw Jobs data as markers on this map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;map2&quot; style=&quot;height: 440px; border: 1px solid #AAA;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-states_stackoverflow.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-c.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-csharp.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-c++.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-c++.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-java.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-objective-c.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-perl.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-python.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-r.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-ruby.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/us-ruby+on+rails.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/markers.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/markers-2.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/leaf-demo.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/jsons/d3_demo.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 15:33:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/jobs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/jobs</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
